A Finding Aid to the Kate Lang Papers, 1921-1996, in the Archives of American Art AAA.langkate
Archives of American Art
Kate Lang papers
1921-1996
AAA.langkate
Archives of American Art
1.1 Linear feet
The papers of self-taught artist Kate Lang consist of a biographical sketch; letters, cards, and instructions from a patron for paintings; notes and other writings; lists of sales and other financial records; newspaper articles about Lang; exhibition announcements; printed source material for paintings; and photographs and snapshots of Lang as a young girl as well as color photographs and snapshots of her artwork. The collection measures 1.1 linear feet and dates from 1921 to 1996.
Kate Lang
Biographical Note
Kate Lang, born Kathryn Louise Barbour in 1910 in Mobile, Alabama, started painting at age 80. A self-taught artist, she sold her paintings at local flea markets (Washington, D.C.'s Eastern Market on Saturdays and Georgetown Market on Sundays) until her death in 1996. Lang excelled at celebrity and pet portraits painted in the style of contemporary folk art. She held exhibitions at Connection Gallery in Washington, D.C. and George Washington University's Dimrock Gallery in 1992 and at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in 1995.
Scope and Content Note
The Kate Lang papers measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1921 to 1996. The collection documents the artistic career and creative process of Arlington, Virginia-based self-taught painter Kate Lang. The collection contains a brief biographical account, scattered professional and personal correspondence, writings and notes with sketches by Kate Lang, financial records, clippings, exhibition announcements, and numerous photographs and snapshots of Kate Lang, her artwork, friends and family. The collection compliments the Archives' material on self-taught artists and provides some useful evidence of an alternative market for painting.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1992 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Letters, 1992-1996, undated (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Writings, 1992-1994, undated (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 4: Financial Records, 1990-1996, undated (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1991-1996, undated (Box 1, OV 2; 5 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, 1921-circa 1990s (Box 1, OV 2; 0.6 linear feet)
Provenance
The papers were donated in 2001 and 2009 by Richard Lang, the son of Kate Lang.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.
Flea markets--Washington (D.C.); Painting, American--Economic aspects; Photographs; Self-taught artists--Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs; Women painters--Washington (D.C.)
- Biographical Material, 1992; Series 1; 1 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains a brief biographical sketch about the life of Kate Lang which appears in the publication Women in Art.
  - Kate Lang Biographical Sketch, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1970-1996, undated; Series 2; 3 Folders Box 1
  Most of the letters to Kate Lang concern art-related matters such as requests for artwork and sales of artwork. There are cards and letters of appreciation from customers as well from the Northern Virginia AIDS ministry and the IONA Senior Services Network in Washington, D.C. for Lang's artwork donations. Also found here is a letter written by Lang to her ex-husband, Jim, regarding mostly financial matters. Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Letters and Cards to Kate Lang, 1992-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Letter to Lang's Ex-Husband, Jim, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1992-1994, undated; Series 3; 6 Folders Box 1
  Writings include notes, sketches, and a layout for a booklet of cartoons Kate Lang hoped to publish. Notes and sketches illustrate dimensions, colors, and inscriptions for artwork requested by a collector as well as sketches and plans for original artwork. This series also includes Lang's work schedules and deadlines she made for herself as well as a writing on the history of her training in art.
  - Sketches and Notes for Cartoon Booklet, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sketches and Notes for Cartoons and Artwork, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes for Al Marzorini's Painting Requests with Instructions, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notes and Sketches for Artwork, and Work Schedules, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Work Schedules and Lists of Artwork to be Done, 1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Writing About Art Training, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial Records, 1990-1996, undated; Series 4; 2 Folders Box 1
  Financial Records include lists and prices of artwork sold, cost of materials used, expenses incurred for flea market trips, living expenses, a reconciliation book for sales made at flea markets, and a 1993 financial statement.
  - Flea Market Costs and Sales; 1993 Financial Statement; Reconciliation Book, 1990-1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Material Costs, Lists of Artwork and Flea Market Items Sold, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Printed Material, 1991-1996, undated; Series 5; 5 Folders Box 1, OV 2
  This series contains newspaper clippings about Kate Lang and her art, her career at the flea markets, and flea markets in general. These clippings are arranged chronologically. There are two folders of newspaper and magazine clippings which Lang used as inspiration and source material for her artwork. These clippings are arranged by subject. There are newsletters, exhibition announcements and catalogs, as well as business cards for Lang's business contacts and for Kate Lang herself.
  - Newspaper Clippings and Business Cards, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings Used as Source Material, 1991-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Oversized Newspaper and Magazine Clippings about Kate Lang, 1992-1996 (Box OV 2)
- Photographs, 1921-circa 1990s, undated; Series 6; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  This series contains original photographs and copies of Kate Lang as a young woman in the 1920s and as an adult in the late 1960s and early 1970s. There is a large photograph of Babe Ruth that Lang likely used as source material. Also found here are dozens of snapshots of artwork, the artist at the flea market, her studio, and an exhibition opening in addition to photographs of Lang with family and friends and several pictures of a memorial party.
  - Kate Lang, 1921-1971 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Kate Lang with Paintings, Friends, and Family, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Kate Lang Exhibitions, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pastels and Exercises, 1924-1927 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Works of Art, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 22-26)
  - Oversized Photograph of Babe Ruth, undated (Box OV 2)